In this two-part
series on gray hair,
I will go through why hair turns grey,
what's the role of genetics,
and what we can do about it.
"Why Does Hair Turn Gray?"
The graying of hair is one of
the most obvious signs of aging.
It's also known by a technical
term that I had never heard of,
"canities."
The first time I saw the word,
I misread it,
wondering what gray hair
had to do with dentistry.
Evidently, gray hair
isn't really white,
but the pale yellowish tinge
of the constitutive
keratin protein,
but, like polar bears,
it just looks white by the way
light reflects off of it.
Why is hair pigmented
in the first place?
Some suggest it may be
for detoxification,
as natural toxins
like heavy metals
bind to the pigment melanin
to be excreted from the body
through hair outgrowth.
That's why you can estimate
the amount of fish consumption
from the mercury content
of children's hair clippings,
why "[a]nalysis of hair mercury
may be warranted
before pregnancy"
in women who eat a lot of fish,
and why the levels
of mercury in the hair
of those eating plant-based
diets were found to be
up to ten times lower than those
who just occasionally ate fish.
Within three months of switching
to a plant-based diet,
the levels of mercury, lead, and
cadmium growing out in your hair
appear to drop significantly
but build back up
when meat and eggs
are added back into the diet.
Enough with the science trivia.
What causes our hair
to turn gray,
and what can we do about it?
In medical school,
you learn about
the so-called 50-50-50 rule.
By the age of 50,
the dictum goes,
50 percent of the population
has at least 50 percent
gray hair.
But that was based on
a homogenous population
of largely white,
fair-haired Australians.
The global range is more like
6 percent to 23 percent
are 50 percent gray by 50.
Though not as memorable
an axiom,
it looks like 75 percent or so
of people 45 to 65 years old
have about 25 percent gray hair.
Those of African
or Asian descent
tend to show less gray hair.
White people generally start
to gray in their mid-30s,
Asians in their late 30s,
and Africans in their mid-40s,
such that premature graying
is defined
before 20 in Caucasians
but before 30
in African Americans.
Age 25 has been suggested
as a cutoff for India.
Premature or not,
what causes hair to turn gray
in the first place?
The hair follicle is
a complex little mini-organ
that anchors and grows
a single hair.
In the base of the follicle bulb
as few as 100
pigment-making cells
normally stain the emerging hair
shaft with melanin pigments
that can range in color
from black to red.
A single hair grows for about
3.5 years before falling out
and a new one starts
growing in its place.
So, graying may start
after about 10 hair cycles
when pigment deposition declines
as the pigment generating cells,
called melanocytes,
start to become depleted.
What kills them off?
There's a depigmentation
disorder called vitiligo
where melanocytes
in the skin are killed off
by the buildup
of hydrogen peroxide,
which can decompose
into toxic free radicals.
So, researchers checked,
and indeed,
the same "massive" levels were
found in aging hair follicles.
Where does the hydrogen peroxide
come from?
It's naturally generated as a
by-product of melanin synthesis,
but normally countered
by an antioxidant enzyme
called catalase.
The problem, it seems,
is that catalase
and other antioxidant defenses
may decline as we age
and leave melanocytes vulnerable
to their own hot potato
production of pigment.
Our own eyelashes present
"an enigma in plain sight."
Eyelashes tend to be the
darkest hairs on the human body
and undergo graying
significantly later
than other hairs.
The explanation appears to be
the presence of a particular
antioxidant protein
missing from regular hair,
consistent with the prevailing
"free radical
theory of graying."